SEUM:
Hello everyone!
This is the first podcast about
Black Hole.
SEUM:
I wanted to create an entire
series about the extreme object
SEUM:
of the universe, and I cannot
think anything but the black
SEUM:
hole first.
Uh, whenever got access to
SEUM:
internet and I heard the black
hole concept, I was totally
SEUM:
obsessed with learning this
object.
SEUM:
And it's kind of a lot of
mystery to me, that moment.
SEUM:
And this is the topic that got
me into the whole astrophysics
SEUM:
thing.
I watched countless documentary
on astrophysics and read many
SEUM:
articles, but it's all started
this on topic black hole.
SEUM:
So today I want to talk about
it.
SEUM:
And before diving into the main
topic, I want you consider that
SEUM:
I'm not a native speaker in
English.
SEUM:
Um, I might make many
grammatical or probably lots of
SEUM:
grammatical mistakes And I'll
probably sometimes run out of
SEUM:
words.
Something like happens like this
SEUM:
that I sometimes I feel, um,
some feels feel the concept, but
SEUM:
I don't, I don't feel the word
for it.
SEUM:
So I might stumble there.
So please consider that I'm a
very beginner at this, and I
SEUM:
hope I'll get better at this
with each iteration.
SEUM:
And with that being said, let's
talk about Black Hole.
SEUM:
Black hole is the object in the
universe that its gravitational
SEUM:
pull is so strong that not even
light can escape.
SEUM:
For every massive object or any
object that has a mass has a
SEUM:
gravitational pull towards it
due to the gravitational pull.
SEUM:
To escape its velocity, you have
to have some amount of escape
SEUM:
velocity.
For example, our Earth has
SEUM:
eleven kilometers per second
escape velocity.
SEUM:
So if you throw an object with
this speed, it's going to go
SEUM:
outside of the Earth's
gravitational field.
SEUM:
And if you keep increasing the
mass of the object.
SEUM:
This velocity will keep
increasing.
SEUM:
So what happens when you put the
mass above the amount When the
SEUM:
when the escape velocity is
equivalent to the speed of
SEUM:
light.
That's when nothing can escape
from its gravitational pull.
SEUM:
But as the highest speed of any
object in our universe can be
SEUM:
occupied as the speed of light,
so nothing can escape from the
SEUM:
gravitational pull of this
object.
SEUM:
The formation of black hole is
whenever when a massive star
SEUM:
collapses under its own gravity.
To give you an overview.
SEUM:
Any type of star has a massive
gravity, and that gravity is,
SEUM:
um, cancelled by the outer
thermal energy push, and that
SEUM:
thermal energy is produced by
the fusion reaction at its core.
SEUM:
Um, for example, our sun uses
hydrogen to helium fusion to
SEUM:
produce that energy so that it
can counteract the inward
SEUM:
gravitational pull.
And when at its core, burns out
the hydrogen, it is going to
SEUM:
burn helium, and each stage it
produces more energy and
SEUM:
sun(star) will get puffed, when
A star runs out of hydrogen,
SEUM:
then it uses helium, and then it
uses carbon, and then it uses
SEUM:
oxygen, and then it uses
silicon, and then finally it
SEUM:
burns the silicon, which means
fuses the silicon to, produces,
SEUM:
uh, some type of metal.
And there is a kind of
transition transition element.
SEUM:
And that transition element
produces the iron.
SEUM:
And this iron is interesting
because when iron fuses it is no
SEUM:
longer an exothermic reaction.
It's an endothermic reaction.
SEUM:
So the combination of two iron
atom is no longer producing
SEUM:
energy.
And you you you need it to
needed that energy to counteract
SEUM:
the gravitational pull.
The massive gravitational pull
of the sun or a star.
SEUM:
So push is no longer provided.
And and the star kind of puffy
SEUM:
because I already mentioned
it's, it's it's in a form of red
SEUM:
giant.
So all of a sudden the star
SEUM:
star's outer layers kind of
collapses without any outward
SEUM:
push.
So and it's collapses and, uh,
at the core is the rigid iron
SEUM:
iron core and all the layers
kind of bounces back to that
SEUM:
rigid iron core.
And that's when the supernova
happens.
SEUM:
Most of the mass of the star is
literally thrown away at the
SEUM:
supernova.
And if the remnant of mass is
greater than the one point four
SEUM:
times the solar mass.
Then electron degeneracy
pressure also fails.
SEUM:
Proton and electron recombine to
create neutron, and all the star
SEUM:
kind of creates the pool full of
neutrons.
SEUM:
So, the neutron star forms.
But if the remnant of the star
is more massive than even two
SEUM:
point two solar masses, the
neutron degeneracy pressure no
SEUM:
longer also holds.
So it kind of collapses under
its own gravity.
SEUM:
And that's when the black hole
forms.
SEUM:
Now we know that how black hole
forms, how do we detect the
SEUM:
black hole if it's totally dark
or kind of, um, as by
SEUM:
definition, black hole, not even
light can escape.
SEUM:
So how do we detect it?
So one of the thing is that we
SEUM:
use to detect it is the
accretion disk.
SEUM:
When a black hole engulf any
other star and sucks its matter
SEUM:
into it, some of the matter
actually, um, actually gets into
SEUM:
its orbit and almost, almost
gets the speed of light, uh,
SEUM:
speed and heats up.
And the disk due to the heat it
radiates the light from it.
SEUM:
It radiates electromagnetic
radiation, visible, infrared,
SEUM:
and even x ray.
So and they're using that
radiation.
SEUM:
We can detect that there is a
black hole at its center.
SEUM:
From the center there is nothing
emitting.
SEUM:
And from the accretion disk
there is light producing.
SEUM:
And another thing we also use to
detect the black hole is the
SEUM:
particular movement of nearby
star.
SEUM:
if the star is moving a
particular orbit, we can use
SEUM:
many star orbit to figure out
how much the mass required that
SEUM:
point to create a, to create a
kind of that, much that amount
SEUM:
of gravitational pull where the
star is rotating that way.
SEUM:
And with that kind of, um,
mathematics.
SEUM:
Probably the Kepler's law.
We can figure out the mass
SEUM:
required into the core, into the
center.
SEUM:
And from that also, we can
detect that there is a massive
SEUM:
object inside, and that massive
object can be only be the black
SEUM:
hole.
So that's how we can also figure
out the black hole's position.
SEUM:
For example, we find out the
Sagittarius A by the particular
SEUM:
movements of the star, uh, at
the core of our galaxy.
SEUM:
And, and this is found out by
the Andrea Ghez and she is given
SEUM:
Nobel Prize for it at twenty
twenty, I guess.
SEUM:
Sagittarius A almost, um, four
million times greater mass than
SEUM:
the sun.
Another way we can detect the
SEUM:
black holes using the
gravitational waves, which is a
SEUM:
modern approach.
And it's quite interesting that
SEUM:
Einstein predicted this at
nineteen sixteen.
SEUM:
And the first evidence for that
came into September fourteen,
SEUM:
twenty fifteen, and almost a
century after the Einstein
SEUM:
predicted that.
It's quite interesting what
happens, in the gravitational
SEUM:
waves that whenever two massive
objects like black hole comes in
SEUM:
contact to its gravitational
pull, they kind of rotates
SEUM:
around orbits, each each other,
and that creates a ripple in the
SEUM:
fabric of space time.
And the the ripples are the
waves in the fabric of space
SEUM:
time, kind of, um, creates the
space, shrinks and expands all
SEUM:
of a sudden.
And that's and that expansion
and the shrinks kind of can be
SEUM:
detected because you put lasers
and if it if it if it there, if
SEUM:
a gravitational wave passes by
and the space will kind of, um,
SEUM:
expand and shrinks down.
So you kind of the distance
SEUM:
between them will kind of, uh,
kind of oscillate And you can
SEUM:
detect that oscillation by using
laser or kind of something that
SEUM:
actually very, Sensitive to
small shifts And using that, we
SEUM:
can also detect the
gravitational.
SEUM:
Object that there is a collision
happening at this, at this mass
SEUM:
Because that amount of amplitude
only created by this amount of
SEUM:
massive object, we can find out
that there is a black hole or
SEUM:
not, or probably there is a
neutron star.
SEUM:
So using gravitational waves we
can also detect there is a black
SEUM:
hole or not.
In fact using gravitational
waves we can detect any massive
SEUM:
or any object that has a mass.
Um, it depends how sensitive our
instruments are to those waves.
SEUM:
So that's another way.
Another way to detect black hole
is by massive object, um, which
SEUM:
is the gravitational lensing.
Whenever a massive objects is
SEUM:
there, space time is gets
curved, and that curvature of
SEUM:
space time creates a lensing
effect.
SEUM:
And that's why you see a black
hole and its other side kind of
SEUM:
warp And you see the accretion
disk is kind of orthogonally
SEUM:
painted at the two side and
other side.
SEUM:
Kind of can be seen.
So that's the gravitational
lensing.
SEUM:
And gravitational lensing can be
detected um, by our telescope.
SEUM:
The background is distorted this
way.
SEUM:
So there must be some kind of
massive object there.
SEUM:
So you can also find out, um, a
black hole by that to whenever
SEUM:
there is an there isn't an
accretion disk present or
SEUM:
something like that happens.
You can find out the black hole
presence.
SEUM:
Another thing happens at near a
black hole is that time
SEUM:
dilation.
I already mentioned that the
massive object curves, the any
SEUM:
object curves the system.
The massive object curves is
very much High So, uh, so
SEUM:
whenever you get to a close to a
black hole, your time will run
SEUM:
slow due to the curvature is
very significant here.
SEUM:
And another thing also happens
is spaghettification, um,
SEUM:
whenever you go near a black
hole, you kind of you're kind of
SEUM:
stressed, uh, in the vertical
direction and squeezed the
SEUM:
horizontal direction due to its
massive gravitational pull
SEUM:
difference difference between
your leg and your head.
SEUM:
So that kind of creates the
spaghettification at the, uh,
SEUM:
black hole.
At the black hole.
SEUM:
And another thing I want I
forgot to mention about the time
SEUM:
dilation is that, any object
creates a curvature of the space
SEUM:
in the space time actually
measured in earth because earth
SEUM:
has a gravitational field and
you go somewhere up, it's your
SEUM:
time is fast compared to the
people on the, the ground.
SEUM:
And this also experimented using
aircraft for the in the aircraft
SEUM:
there, or the atomic clock, and
that atomic clock and two
SEUM:
identical two identical atomic
clock is created.
SEUM:
And one at the ground atomic
clock actually run sometime some
SEUM:
very, uh, low some amount of
time slower than the the which
SEUM:
runs the at the airplane.
So that actually checks out that
the time shifts in the gravity
SEUM:
gravitational pull any object
that has a gravitational pull.
SEUM:
And that also happens the people
on the satellite, uh, ISIS uh,
SEUM:
have more, faster time going
than the people on the Earth.
SEUM:
So there's another So I talked a
lot about.
SEUM:
But I never forget one of the
more important thing that the
SEUM:
black hole.
Regardless, this is a very
extreme object in the universe.
SEUM:
It's quite simple, actually, and
because it has only three
SEUM:
properties, that is charge,
spin, and mass.
SEUM:
So that's only three properties
you need to describe any black
SEUM:
hole.
And.
SEUM:
These factor only decides how
many lifetime it will last, or
SEUM:
what will happen if there is
nothing to engulf by the black
SEUM:
hole.
So if not, even light can escape
the black hole.
SEUM:
Doesn't that mean that the black
hole will keep getting bigger
SEUM:
and bigger in size, as
everything is just going in, but
SEUM:
nothing comes out?
Then isn't black hole will live
forever.
SEUM:
It turns out that's not true.
In nineteen seventy four,
Stephen Hawking came up with the
SEUM:
concept of Hawking radiation,
and according to that, a black
SEUM:
hole also emits radiation and
its radiation is disproportional
SEUM:
with its mass.
This means that more massive
black hole is lesser the
SEUM:
radiation it will emit.
So, from at the at the end the
SEUM:
radiation emitted by a black
hole at its lifetime will be
SEUM:
exponential.
If it doesn't fit any more and
gets more massive than the black
SEUM:
hole will slowly start to emit
radiation and and with its mass
SEUM:
decreasing, it will radiate more
and more faster.
SEUM:
At the and at the end of its
lifetime, it will create a
SEUM:
spectacular bang.
And that's how the black hole
SEUM:
dies eventually, at the very
further and further of the
SEUM:
universe's lifetime.
And this is really bigger scale
of time we are talking about.
SEUM:
As everything falls into a black
hole.
SEUM:
It might seem like the
information is getting erased.
SEUM:
And according to the information
theory, no information cannot be
SEUM:
erased from the universe.
Or if you are not an information
theory fan.
SEUM:
Entropy of the universe cannot
be decreased.
SEUM:
For example, if you throw a
system like Earth which is very
SEUM:
disordered state, and throw it
into a black hole, it might seem
SEUM:
like that the entropy of the
universe lowered.
SEUM:
and according to the
thermodynamic principle, entropy
SEUM:
cannot be lowered.
So what happening?
SEUM:
What actually happening that
point.
SEUM:
And to preserve the information
theory and thermodynamic
SEUM:
principle.
Um, Gerard t Hooft and Leonard
Susskind, at probably nineteen
SEUM:
ninety, came up with the idea
that the black hole, the
SEUM:
information gate into black hole
actually is not lost.
SEUM:
They are encoded at the surface
of the black hole event horizon.
SEUM:
And that information will again
get shoot back with the Hawking
SEUM:
radiation.
That I described earlier.
SEUM:
And so information theory is
preserved.
SEUM:
In this way.
So that's it about the overview
of Black Hole.
SEUM:
And the next session I'm
probably going to discuss more
SEUM:
details of each stage.
For example, there's a lot to
SEUM:
learn about how black hole
formation happened and also the
SEUM:
Hawking radiation.
There's a lot to learn.
SEUM:
So I think I'm going to discuss
them later.
SEUM:
And until that, take care.
And consider supporting me if
you think my efforts are useful